Guide to Galt Brothers Hardware records 1910-1971
Montana Historical Society
Galt Brothers Hardware records
1910-1971, bulk 1910-1956
Montana Historical Society Archives
MC 344
Galt Brothers Hardware (Stanford, Mont.)
6.5 linear feet
The Galt Brothers of Stanford, Montana, owned a hardware store, a drayage business, a farm/ranch, and a Ford auto dealership. This collection consists of records of those businesses.
Historical Note
Galt Brothers was founded about 1910 by Henry H. (1886-1986), Errol F. (1889-1975), and Oliver J. (1891?-1986) Galt, all born in Minnesota, sons of William and Emeretta (Robinson) Galt. Younger brother Glen A. Galt (1894-1986) later joined his brothers in the business. The store specialized in hardware and agricultural implements. In 1917 Errol sold out his share of the store to open the First National Bank in Geyser. Henry also sold out his share to concentrate on the cattle business. O. J. Galt retired from the store about 1980. The store continued under new ownership as the Pioneer Hardware Store.
In addition to the hardware business, the brothers ran a drayage business, a cattle ranch, and a Ford automobile dealership and garage. Oliver primarily ran the hardware store and drayage business, Henry the ranch, and Glen the garage, but all four brothers were involved in all aspects of the family enterprises.
This collection consists of financial records (1910-1965) and related correspondence of the Galt brothers' various businesses. There are five subgroups.
The Galt Brothers Hardware subgroup (1910-1958) constitutes the bulk of the collection. It consists of general correspondence (1914-1947), arranged alphabetically within several groups; court papers (1920-1940), predominantly bankruptcy proceedings for customers; financial records (1910-1958) including cash books, daybook/journals, general ledgers, invoice registers, invoices, note registers, trial balances, and other items; and subject files, primarily re U. S. World War II government programs.
There is a small subgroup of Oliver J. Galt personal papers (1921-1942), including correspondence, invoices, and legal documents.
The O. J. Galt Drayage business subgroup (1921-1942) includes general ledgers, a journal, invoices, and a report to the Montana Board of Railroad Commissioners.
The Galt Brothers farm/ranch business subgroup (1921-1965) includes general ledgers, a journal, records for the sale and shipment of livestock, and subject files on various government agricultural programs.
The Ford Dealership/Galt Brothers Garage subgroup (1917-1918, 1939) consists of a small number of letters, invoices, and legal documents.
Arranged by subgroup and series. Some material housed in Manuscript Volumes. See location of Collection above and inventory below for more information.
Collection is open for research
Acquisition information available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Stanford (Mont.)--History
Automobile dealers--Montana--Stanford; Freight and freightage--Montana--Stanford; Hardware stores--Montana--Stanford; Ranches--Montana--Judith Basin County
Montana; Agriculture; Ranching; Retail Trade
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Galt Brothers Hardware, 1910-1958
  - Biographical Materials
    - Obituaries and biographical sketches for William W. Galt, Henry H. Galt, Errol F. Galt, Oliver J. Galt, and Glen A. Galt, 1913-1986 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - General Correspondence
    - B-M (correspondents include G. E. Addy, J. I. Case Company, F. B. Connelly Company, DeLaval Separator Company, E. F. Galt, Home Owners Loan Corporation, Mrs. Bernard W. Jenkins, Judith Basin County Agricultural Conservation Association, Fred B. Lind, Joe McInnis, Midland Implement Company, Minneapolis-Moline Power Implement Company, Montana County Extension Service), 1914-1939 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
    - N-Y (correspondents include Art Norton, Pennsylvania Rubber Company, Pure Oil Company, St. Louis Electrical Works, Simmons Hardware Company, State Building and Loan Association, Charles A. Stickney Company, Iven Tucker, Roland Turner, Vermont Loan and Trust Company, E. L. Voth, Western Retail Lumbermen's Association), 1914-1939 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
    - J. I. Case Company, 1941-1943 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
    - Great Falls Paper Company, 1946 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
    - Midland Implement Company, 1941-1947 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
    - U. S. War Production Board and Office of Production Management circulars, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
    - B-W (correspondents include Bartol Ranch, Ben Hur Trailers, Federal Reserve Bank of Kansas City, Fort Missoula, General Manufacturing Company, Mrs. Paul Jurasch Jr., Fred B. Lind, Lindsay Bros. Co., Majestic Manufacturing Company, Minneapolis-Moline Power Implement Company, Montana Board of Equalization, Montana Fish and Game Commission, O. Petesch, Reynold Plath, J. M. Riedlinger, William Skarda, U. S. Office of Price Administration, U. S. Dept. of Agriculture War Board, John Valentine, E. L. Voth, West Fargo Manufacturing Company), 1940-1947 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
    - A-W (re debt collections), 1916-1937 (Box-folder 1 / 9-10)
    - Telegrams (scattered), 1914-1940 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - Court Papers
    - Bankruptcy proceedings, circa 1920-1940 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
    - Galt Brothers vs. F. M. Bennett, circa 1931 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
  - Financial Records
    - Accounts charged off to loss, circa 1956-1971 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
    - Cash book, 1912-1916 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
    - Cash books, 1922-1936 (Box-folder 2 / 1-6)
    - Cash books, 1937-1943 (Box-folder 3 / 1-4)
    - Check stubs, 1918-1921 (Box-folder 3 / 5)
    - Debt collections, 1930-1939, 1955 (Box-folder 3 / 6)
    - Daybooks, 1922-1949 (Box-folder 4 / 1-6)
    - Daybook, 1949-1955 (Box-folder 5 / 1)
    - Freight bills: Great Northern Railway (scattered), 1915-1946 (Box-folder 5 / 2)
    - General ledger, circa 1912-1913 (Volume 1)
    - General ledgers, circa 1915-1918, 1923-1924 (Box-folder 5 / 3-5)
    - General ledgers, 1927-1928, 1932, 1934 (Box-folder 6 / 1-4)
    - General ledgers, 1938-1939, 1942, 1949, 1954 (Box-folder 7 / 1-5)
    - General ledger, 1958 (Box-folder 8 / 1)
    - Hail adjustment proof of loss, 1944 (Box-folder 8 / 2)
    - Insurance, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 8 / 3)
    - Inventories, 1914-1921 (Box-folder 8 / 4-9)
    - Inventory: East Side Store, 1920-1921 (Box-folder 8 / 10)
    - Inventory: guns, 1941, undated (Box-folder 8 / 11)
    - Invoice ledger, 1910-1912 (Box-folder 8 / 12)
    - Invoice ledgers, 1912-1914, 1918-1927 (Box-folder 9 / 1-3)
    - Invoices and orders [sampled], 1913-1944, 1967 (Box-folder 9 / 4-10)
    - Minneapolis-Moline Power Implement Company orders, 1944 (Box-folder 9 / 11)
    - Note register, 1915-1919 (Box-folder 10 / 1)
    - Order book, 1924-1925 (Box-folder 10 / 2)
    - Price lists, circa 1938-1942 (Box-folder 10 / 3)
    - Promissory notes, 1933-1942 (Box-folder 10 / 4)
    - Receipts, 1922-1946 (Box-folder 10 / 5-6)
    - Trial balance books, 1912-1924 (Volume 2-7)
    - Trial balance books, 1930-1949 (Volume 8-9)
  - Legal Documents
    - Miscellaneous (includes Errol F. Galt's sale of his interest in business, dealers' sales contracts, refund on gasoline license tax, mortgage), 1917-1946 (Box-folder 10 / 7)
      RESTRICTED
  - Reports
    - Census of business report, 1939 (Box-folder 10 / 8)
    - Reports to Montana Unemployment Compensation Commission, 1941-1944 (Box-folder 10 / 9)
  - Subject Files
    - Burlap wool bags (includes certificates and government wartime regulations), 1939-1942 (Box-folder 10 / 10)
    - Montana Seed Law, 1940-1942 (Box-folder 10 / 11)
    - Veterans Welfare Commission, 1946 (Box-folder 10 / 12)
    - Westinghouse lamps agency, 1939 (Box-folder 10 / 13)
    - War Food Administration purchase certificates for rationed farm equipment, 1944 (Box-folder 10 / 14)
    - World War II taxes (includes retail excise, telephone, income, victory), 1941-1944 (Box-folder 10 / 15)
  - Miscellany
    - Miscellaneous (includes Montana Board of Railroad Commissioners order re motor carrier insurance, Rocky Mountain Sportsmen's Association petition, Extension Service newsletter, raffle prize), 1937-1942 (Box-folder 10 / 16)
- Oliver J. Galt, Personal, 1921-1942
  - General Correspondence
    - Chronological, 1925-1942 (Box-folder 10 / 17)
  - Financial Records
    - Invoices and receipts, 1921-1940 (Box-folder 10 / 18)
    - Promissory notes, 1933-1941 (Box-folder 10 / 19)
  - Legal Documents
    - Mortgage, contract, 1938-1942 (Box-folder 10 / 20)
  - Miscellany
    - House plan, undated (Box-folder 10 / 21)
- Oliver J. Galt, Drayage Business, 1926-1944
  - General Correspondence
    - Montana Board of Railroad Commissioners, Tintinger Gravel Company, 1938-1939 (Box-folder 11 / 1)
  - Financial Records
    - General ledgers, 1926-1937 (Box-folder 11 / 2-5)
    - Insurance, 1937 (Box-folder 11 / 6)
    - Invoices (mostly undated), circa 1926-1944 (Box-folder 11 / 7)
    - Journal, 1928-1929 (Box-folder 12 / 1)
  - Reports
    - Quarterly and annual reports to Montana Board of Railroad Commissioners, 1941-1944 (Box-folder 12 / 2)
- Galt Brothers Farm and Ranch Business, 1921-1965
  - General Correspondence
    - Chronological, 1930-1933, 1943 (Box-folder 12 / 3)
  - Financial Records
    - General ledgers (also includes O. J. Galt personal and drayage records), 1954-1955, 1965 (Box-folder 12 / 4-6)
    - Grain elevator receipts, 1930, 1941-1945 (Box-folder 13 / 1)
    - Hail insurance proof of loss, 1939 (Box-folder 13 / 2)
    - Invoices (scattered), 1921-1934 (Box-folder 13 / 3)
    - Journal (mostly empty, includes several pages concerning cattle sales and shipments), 1927-1928 (Box-folder 13 / 4)
    - Sales of cattle, 1928-1939 (Box-folder 13 / 5-7)
    - Sales of fur (includes skunk, weasel, and wolf), 1934-1937 (Box-folder 13 / 8)
    - Sales of hogs, 1929-1930, undated (Box-folder 13 / 9)
    - Sales of steer hides, 1929-1930, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 13 / 10)
  - Subject Files
    - Federal Agricultural Credit Corporation loan for range cattle (Jessie Galt), 1933-1934 (Box-folder 13 / 11)
    - U. S. Agricultural Adjustment Administration (includes Federal Crop Insurance), 1933-1944 (Box-folder 13 / 12)
    - U. S. Commodity Credit Corporation, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 13 / 13)
    - U. S. Farm Security Administration, 1939, undated (Box-folder 13 / 14)
    - U. S. Office of Defense Transportation, 1943 (Box-folder 13 / 15)
    - World War II farm programs, 1941-1944, undated (Box-folder 13 / 16)
  - Miscellany
    - Beef inspection certificates, 1930-1939, 1945 (Box-folder 13 / 17)
- Ford Garage and Dealership (Glen A. Galt), 1917-1918, 1939
  - General Correspondence
    - Chronological, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 13 / 18)
  - Financial Records
    - Invoices (scattered), 1917-1918 (Box-folder 13 / 19)
  - Legal Documents
    - Distributor's agreement with Pennsylvania Rubber Company; conditional sales contract on trucks, 1917, 1939 (Box-folder 13 / 20)